Guide to the Richard Foreman and Kate Manheim Papers MSS.152
Fales Library and Special Collections
- Series IX: General Theater Related Material
  - "Theatre National de L'Opera", 1993 (Box 39, Folder 1913)
  - Atlas, Charles. "More Men" at 319 W. 14, undated (Box 39, Folder 1914)
  - Amazing Soviet Circus at Madison Square Garden., undated (Box 39, Folder 1915)
  - Anderson, Laurie. Press release, "United States Part II" at The Kitchen., undated (Box 39, Folder 1916)
  - "Baal" program, undated (Box 39, Folder 1917)
  - "1793 La Citerevolutionnaire est de ce monde" at Theatre du Soleil., undated (Box 39, Folder 1918)
  - Claude, Paul. "Tete d'or", undated (Box 39, Folder 1919)
  - "Dom Juan" at Theatre de Gennevilliers., undated (Box 39, Folder 1920)
  - Follies Bergere, undated (Box 39, Folder 1921)
  - Cortez, Diego. Artists Space Film series., undated (Box 39, Folder 1922)
  - Edern-Hallier, Jean. Maison Francaise at Columbia University., undated (Box 39, Folder 1923)
  - Foucault, Michel. Reception held by New York University French Department., undated (Box 39, Folder 1924)
  - Foucher, Michelle. "La Table paroles de femmes" at the French Institute., undated (Box 39, Folder 1925)
  - Gajek, George., undated (Box 39, Folder 1926)
  - Hyedann, Stella. "Gesture adn Voice" at 56 Lispenard St., undated (Box 39, Folder 1927)
  - Journee Nationale d'Action, undated (Box 39, Folder 1928)
  - Kristeva, Julia. Invitation to a reception celebrating the publication of Desire in Language., undated (Box 39, Folder 1929)
  - Mangolte, Babette. "What Maisie Knew" screening at Anthology Film Archives, undated (Box 39, Folder 1930)
  - Morrison, Richard. "2, an Installation tragedy" at 8 W. 8th st., undated (Box 39, Folder 1931)
  - New York State Small Press Association. Invitation from David Kermani and John Ashberg to the 1 year anniversary celebration., undated (Box 39, Folder 1932)
  - The New York Theater of the Obvious, "The Roman Polanski Story", undated (Box 39, Folder 1933)
  - Nitsch, Herman and Steve Poleski. Art of New York Special Events Guide., undated (Box 39, Folder 1934)
  - Nuova Compagnia di Canto Populare, undated (Box 39, Folder 1935)
  - "Ondekoza", undated (Box 39, Folder 1936)
  - "Joe Papp Sings" at the Ballroom, music arranged by S. Silverman., undated (Box 39, Folder 1937)
  - The Performance Group. Materials include: "Point Judith", "Cops", "Nyatt School", "Nostalgia for the future", "Oedipus", program notes to unknown play involving Spalding Gray., undated (Box 39, Folder 1938)
  - Pirandello, Luigi at Centre Dramatique National des Alpes, undated (Box 39, Folder 1939)
  - "Prommation du Mois d'aout a Campagne Premiere", undated (Box 39, Folder 1940)
  - Rainer, Yvonne. "This is a story of a woman who" at Theater for the New City., undated (Box 39, Folder 1941)
  - Renaud, Madeleine. Dinner in honor of Madeleine Renaud hosted by Permanent Representative of French Universities in the US, undated (Box 39, Folder 1942)
  - "Les Spectacles en Asie" at Cinematheque Francaise., undated (Box 39, Folder 1943)
  - Theater of Dr. Dapertutto. "Death and Devil" at Baca Downtown Cultural center in Brooklyn., undated (Box 39, Folder 1944)
  - Theatre of Musical Optics" presents "Midnight Concert" and "Dracula", undated (Box 39, Folder 1945)
  - Theater of Occupational Therapy, undated (Box 39, Folder 1946)
  - Tong, Winston. "Two pieces" at La Mama, undated (Box 39, Folder 1947)
  - "Uncle Mario" at Theater for the New City., undated (Box 39, Folder 1948)
  - White, Diane. Danish art opening, gift from White., undated (Box 39, Folder 1949)
  - "Women and MEn on the Bring" at Clear Space, 54 Franklin St., undated (Box 39, Folder 1950)
- Series X: Grants, Fellowships and Awards
  Series X: Grants, Fellowships, and Awards, includes materials documenting grant and awards given to Richard Foreman and the Ontological-Hysteric Theatre as well as materials documenting benefits for the Ontological-Hysteric Theater. Items range from photographs, newspaper press, newsletters and award certificates to grant applications and correspondence. Subseries A: Award Certificates and Photographs, include plaques, certificates and degrees awarded to Richard Foreman. Subseries B: Press, includes press documentation of Richard Foreman's reception of these awards. Subseries C: Application and Nomination materials, documents the application process for several grants. Subseries D: Benefits for the Ontological-Hysteric Theater, includes fundraising events for the OH Theater.
  - Subseries A: Award certificates and photographs
    - Show Business Award from the Entertainment Editors, LEo Schull and Staff., 1977 (Box 39, Folder 1954)
    - "Kudos" plaque to Richard Foreman, Director., 1981 (Box 39, Folder 1955)
    - Village Theater Awards, "Egyptology", 1983 (Box 39, Folder 1956)
    - Color photograph of Richard Foreman with John E. [illegible], incribed "Richard-An award richly deserved. Congratulations", 1990 (Box 39, Folder 1957)
    - American Academy of Arts and Letters Award, 1992 (Box 39, Folder 1958)
    - Honorary degree from Brown University., 1993 (Box 39, Folder 1960)
    - The Edwin Boorth Award, given by the students of the Ph.D. program in Theatre of the Graduate School and Unieversity Center of the City University of New York., 1997 (Box 39, Folder 1961)
    - Village Voice OBIE, Best Play "Pearls for Pigs" and "Benita Canova", 1997-1998 (Box 39, Folder 1962)
    - PEN Award, Master American Dramatist., 2001 (Box 39, Folder 1963)
    - Henry Hewes Award for Noteworthy Effects in "Panic!", 2003 (Box 39, Folder 1965)
  - Subseries B: Press
    - SoHo Weekly News, Theater Ten Best Lists. Includes "Pandering to the Masses", "Rhoda in Potatoland" and "Hotel for Criminals", 1976 (Box 39, Folder 1966)
    - OBIE press, 1976 (Box 39, Folder 1967)
    - OBIE press, 1987 (Box 39, Folder 1968)
    - American Academy of Arts and Letters press, 1992 (Box 39, Folder 1970)
    - MacArthur grants press coverage, 1995 (Box 39, Folder 1971)
    - OBIE press, 1996 (Box 39, Folder 1972)
    - Pen Literary Awards, press, 2001 (Box 39, Folder 1973)
    - France's Order of Arts and Letters, press, 2003 (Box 39, Folder 1974)
  - Subseries C: Application and nomination materials
    - CAPS grant application, 1976 (Box 39, Folder 1975)
    - CAPS, returned manuscript galley proofs., 1976 (Box 39, Folder 1976)
    - CAPS manuscript submission and response, 1976 (Box 39, Folder 1977)
    - CAPS directory, Plays by fellowship recipients and semi-finalists., 1976-1978 (Box 39, Folder 1978)
    - NEA tentative recommendation memorandum., 1976 (Box 39, Folder 1979)
    - Photocopies of writing, labeled "Rockefeller Fellowship", undated (Box 39, Folder 1980)
  - Subseries D: Benefits for the Ontological Hysteric Theater
    - Ontological-Hysteric Theater fundraising appeal featuring Philip Glass, Eric Bogosian, David Salle., 1991 (Box 39, Folder 1983)
    - Ontological Hysteric Theater fundraising, letter with contribution., 1992 (Box 39, Folder 1984)
    - Ontological-Hysteric Theater fundraising campaign. "The Mind King", undated (Box 39, Folder 1986)
- Series XI: Miscellaneous
  Series XI: Miscellaneous, contains a variety of materials related to Richard Foreman's professional career but outside the scope of previous series. Subseries A: Administrative and Professional Material about Richard Foreman, includes documents such as Richard Forman's curriculum vitae and bibliography. Subseries B: Administrative Materials related to the Ontological Hysteric Theater, this very limited amount of material documents the location and booking side of Theater. Subseries C: Correspondence includes fan mail, hate mail and requests to work with Richard Foreman. Subseries D: Political Materials, documents Richard Foreman's political involvement and consequent public perception. Subseries E: Printed Material, includes printed material with no clear relationship to Foreman or the Ontologicla Hysteric Theater.
  - Subseries A: Administrative and Professional information about Richard Foreman
    - Performing Artservices portfolio., undated (Box 39, Folder 1987)
    - List of works by Richard Foreman, undated (Box 39, Folder 1988)
    - List of characters and performers in Richard Foreman works., undated (Box 39, Folder 1989)
    - Richard Foreman's CV including bibliography and a list of plays (Box 39, Folder 1990)
    - Additions to bibliography, undated (Box 39, Folder 1991)
    - notes and lists, undated (Box 39, Folder 1992)
    - Rome Itinerary, 1992 (Box 39, Folder 1993)
    - Fales Collection Richard Foreman texts (Box 70)
      Format: Zip Disk, Brand: iomega, Size: 100MB
  - Subseries B: Administrative Materials related to the Ontological Hysteric Theatre.
    - Ontological-Hysteric Theatre, 1971 (Box 39, Folder 1994)
    - Richard Foreman 20th Year of Theater Making, 1987 (Box 39, Folder 1995)
    - "RF Spaces", undated (Box 39, Folder 1996)
    - Ontological-Hysteric moves to St. Mark's Church., 1991 (Box 39, Folder 1997)
  - Subseries C: Correspondence
    - Business correspondence, undated (Box 39, Folder 1998)
    - requests to work with Richard Foreman, undated (Box 39, Folder 1999)
    - Critiques, undated (Box 39, Folder 2001)
    - Fan mail, undated (Box 39, Folder 2002)
    - Swiss correspondence, 1978 (Box 39, Folder 2003)
    - letter to Mary from unknown sender, with diagram., undated (Box 39, Folder 2004)
    - French Correspondence., undated (Box 39, Folder 2005)
    - Letter to Richard Foreman from Mark Rappaport regarding "Rock Hudson's Home Movies"., 1992 (Box 39, Folder 2006)
  - Subseries D: Political materials
    - "Traitor List" from probush.com. Includes Richard Foreman., 2003 (Box 39, Folder 2008)
  - Subseries E: Printed Material
    - Privat Kredit Bank. Brochure, 1977 (Box 39, Folder 2009)
    - Iconoclast, November 1986 (Box 39, Folder 2012)
    - B (Box 39, Folder 2013)
    - Bottom Line Tomorrow. v. 11 n. 2, 2003 (Box 39, Folder 2014)
    - European Trash Cinema video catalog, undated (Box 39, Folder 2015)
    - Hudson River Valley vacation and lodging brochures., undated (Box 39, Folder 2016)
    - Narcisse by Bernard lambert. Dust Jacket prints., undated (Box 39, Folder 2017)
    - Questions-Responses. French text., undated (Box 39, Folder 2018)
    - Rose-Croix, Ancien et Mystique Odre de La Rose Croix., undated (Box 39, Folder 2019)
    - Silverlake Project: photocopied pages from "The Myth of the New Man", undated (Box 39, Folder 2020)
    - Articles about Gertrude Stein. Authors includ W. C. Williams, W. Glass, R. Bridgman., undated (Box 39, Folder 2021)
    - miscellaneous fragments, undated (Box 39, Folder 2022)
- Series XII: Biographical
  >Series XII: Biographical Material, documents Richard Foreman's personal life through photographs, educational documents and scrapbooks. In addition, materials related to theater productions Richard Foreman participated in during high school and college appear in this series. These materials are arranged chronologically, where possible. Subseries A: Photographs, includes photographs of Richard Foreman as a child as well as personal snapshots. Subseries B: Richard Foreman's Education, documents Richard Foreman's educational progress and achievements beginning with elementary school and ending with graduate work. Subseries C: Richard Foreman's Early Arts Involvement, includes documentation of Richard Foreman's arts involvement as an actor, a singer and a writer. Subseries D: Family Related Documents, includes materials related to the lives and achievements of Richard Foreman's family.
  - Subseries A: Photographs
    - Black and white photograph of Richard Foreman as a toddler. Removed from frame., undated (Box 39, Folder 2023)
    - Black adn white photographs, one of Richard Foreman as a toddler, the other of building. Removed from single frame, image of building behind the RF photograph., undated (Box 39, Folder 2024)
    - Black and white photographs of Richard and Leslie Foreman. Removed from miniature photo album titled "My Grandchildren", undated (Box 39, Folder 2025)
    - Black and white photographs of Richard and Leslie Forman. Removed from trifold frame., undated (Box 39, Folder 2026)
    - Black and white photographs at Leslie Foreman's wedding. Includes case., undated (Box 39, Folder 2027)
    - Black and white portrait of Richard Foreman and Amy Taubin at their wedding. Includes case., undated (Box 39, Folder 2028)
    - Color photograph of an unidentified man and woman in lounge chairs. [still in frame, frame nailed shut, possible mold in frame?], undated (Box 39, Folder 2029)
    - Foreman family Christmas card, undated (Box 39, Folder 2030)
    - Black and white and sepia toned images of Richard Foreman as a child. (Box 39, Folder 2031)
    - Black and white candid photographs of Richard Foreman as a baby with his family at Lake Hopatcong, New Jersey., 1938 (Box 39, Folder 2032)
    - Black and white photographs of Richard Foreman as a teen., undated (Box 39, Folder 2033)
    - Black adn white portraits of Richard Foreman, Leslie Foreman and Mrs. Foreman. (Box 39, Folder 2034)
    - Black and white portraits of Richard Foreman's mother., undated (Box 39, Folder 2035)
    - Black and white portrait of Richard Foreman's father., undated (Box 39, Folder 2036)
    - Black adn white candid photographs of the Foremans. With a birthday card., ca 1941 (Box 39, Folder 2037)
    - Candid, color phtographs of Richard Foreman's parents, ca 1982 (Box 39, Folder 2038)
    - Black and white images ca 1907. [perhaps Albert Foreman] (Box 39, Folder 2039)
    - Color photographs of a house at two different times. [Possibly the Foreman home in Scarsdale], undated (Box 39, Folder 2040)
    - Color snapshots and negatives of a boat trip., undated (Box 39, Folder 2041)
  - Subseries B: Richard Foreman's Education
    - Elementary school including grades and health., 1943-1949 (Box 40, Folder 2042)
    - Grade reports, Scarsdale High School, 1951-1955 (Box 40, Folder 2043)
    - Scarsdale High School Diploma, 1955 (Box 40, Folder 2044)
    - Copy of letter from Brown University designating Richard Foreman a University Scholar with a small black and white portrait photograph., 1955 (Box 40, Folder 2045)
    - Correspondence from Brown University, 1955-1957 (Box 40, Folder 2046)
    - Brown University grade reports., 1955-1959 (Box 40, Folder 2047)
    - Brown University degrees with honors information, 1956 (Box 40, Folder 2048)
    - Term paper for class in the Art Department. Research copies and original., 1956 (Box 40, Folder 2049)
    - Phi Beta Kappa membership letter, 1959 (Box 40, Folder 2050)
    - Yale re-admission letter., 1960 (Box 40, Folder 2051)
  - Subseries C: Richard Foreman's early arts involvement
    - Jabberwock, Scarsdale High School literary journal. Removed from inside cover of blue high school scrapbook in folder 2054. Richard Foreman contributed as Associate Editor and as Editor-in-Chief., 1954-1955 (Box 40, Folder 2052)
    - Choir photographs. Removed from inside cover of blue high school scrapbook in folder 2054, ca 1954-1955 (Box 40, Folder 2053)
    - Blue high school scrapbook, includes programs, clippings and other documentation of Richard Foreman's arts involvement at Scarsdale High School, 1954-1955 (Box 41, Folder 2054)
    - Black and white photographs of Richard Foreman in "Death of a Salesman' at Brown University., 1955 (Box 40, Folder 2055)
    - Letter to Kate Manheim dated 27 May 1991 and a black and white photograph of Richard Foreman in "Death of a Salesman" at Brown University in 1955. (Box 40, Folder 2056)
    - Black scrapbook. Includes photographs, programs, clippings and other documentation of Richard Foreman's theater involvement at Brown University as well as Amy Taubin's theater performances from the same time., 1955-1967 (Box 42, Folder 2057)
    - Black and white photograph of Richard Foreman in "Time of your life" at Brown University in 1956. (Box 40, Folder 2058)
  - Subseries D:Family related documents
    - Leslie Foreman, education related documents including College Honors and Commencement Program, 1963 (Box 40, Folder 2060)
    - Correspondence between Claire Foreman and New York University School of Law regarding a scholarship endowment., 1966 (Box 40, Folder 2061)
    - Leslie Foreman's engagement announcement in the New York Times and Reporter Dispatch., 1967 (Box 40, Folder 2062)
    - Amy Taubin press and playbill from "The Prime of Miss Jean Brodie", 1968 (Box 40, Folder 2063)
    - Two tickets, marked "Taubin 10 pl Thursday 29 1975" (Box 40, Folder 2064)
    - Albert Foreman's obituary in the New York Times, 1 February 1992. (Box 40, Folder 2065)
    - Trees for Israel certificate. Two trees planted in memory of Claire and Albert Foreman from Richard and Kate, Leslie and David., undated (Box 40, Folder 2066)
    - Albert Foreman's business card., undated (Box 40, Folder 2067)
- Series XIII: Kate Manheim
  Series XIII: Kate Manheim, contains materials related to Kate Manheim's professional career, including but not limited to her work in Richard Foreman's plays. Although materials connected to Kate Manheim appear throughout the collection, this series reflects the grouping of materials relating to Kate Manhiem in the collection's original organization. Subseries A: Prompt Scripts and Personal notes, includes Kate Manheim's prompt scripts as well as production notebooks containing personal notes as well as Richard Foreman's corrections and stage directions. This subseries is arranged alphabetically by play title and all of the contents involve Richard Foreman productions. Subseries B: Notes and Notebooks, includes notebooks that were not clearly designated as relating to a specific play. Additionally, these notebooks arrived grouped together in ziplock bags, separate from the script material. As a result, they remain in a subseries of their own. Subseries C: Production Materials, includes some press and memorabilia related to Foreman plays. Subseries D: Photographs, primarily documents Kate Manheim on stage.Subseries E: Other Projects, includes Kate Manheim's involvement in projects not directly related to Richard Foreman such as her own painting and her work with Heiner Muller. Subseries F: General Press and Interviews, contains articles about and interviews with Kate Manheim. Subseries G: General Theater Related Material, includes programs, publicity and other materials from theater productions and performance pieces by other artists. Materials are arranged chronologically by year. Undated materials appear at the end of the series arranged alphabetically by performer. Subseries H: Awards and Grants, includes awards Kate Manheim received as well as some grantwriting advice. >Subseries I: Biographical Material, this very small series includes materials related to the lives of Kate Manheim and her family. Subseries J: Miscellaneous, contains materials that fell outside the scope of the previous subseries such as printed material, memorabilia, and notes.
  - Subseries A: Prompt Scripts and Personal Notes
    - "The Birth of the Poet" bilingual Dutch script, 1984 (Box 40, Folder 2068)
    - "Birth fo the Poet" Script, Act I: Overture, undated (Box 40, Folder 2069)
    - "The Birth of the Poet" script, Act II, undated (Box 40, Folder 2070)
    - 'The Birth of the Poet" script, Act III., undated (Box 40, Folder 2071)
    - "The Birth of the Poet" script, Act III, undated (Box 40, Folder 2072)
    - "Book of Splendors" annotated folder., undated (Box 40, Folder 2073)
    - "Book of Splendors I" annotated working script p. 1-8, undated (Box 40, Folder 2074)
    - "Book of Splendors I" annotated working script p 9-17, undated (Box 40, Folder 2075)
    - "Book of Splendors I" annotated working script p. 18-26, undated (Box 40, Folder 2076)
    - "Book of Splendors I" annotated French script., undated (Box 40, Folder 2077)
    - "Book of Splendors I" annotated French script. Includes folder labeled "Kate #2 Ne Pas Toucher", undated (Box 40, Folder 2078)
    - "Book of Splendors" miscellaneous notes, undated (Box 40, Folder 2079)
    - "Book of Splendors I" notebook., undated (Box 40, Folder 2080)
    - "Book of Splendors I" notebook., undated (Box 40, Folder 2081)
    - "Book of Splendors I" notebook., undated (Box 40, Folder 2082)
    - "Book of Splendors II" annotated prompt script., undated (Box 40, Folder 2083)
    - "Book of Splendors II" faxed script with ink annotations. Folder includes originals and research copy., undated (Box 40, Folder 2084)
    - "Book of Splendors II" prompt script, hand written., undated (Box 40, Folder 2085)
    - "Book of Splendors II" annotated working script, undated (Box 40, Folder 2086)
    - "Book of Splendors II" working script p. 17-25, undated (Box 40, Folder 2087)
    - "Book of Splendors II" Annotated script., undated (Box 40, Folder 2088)
    - "Book of Splendors II" annotated script., undated (Box 40, Folder 2089)
    - "Book of Splendors II" annotated script., undated (Box 40, Folder 2090)
    - "Blvd de Paris' #1, annotated script, undated (Box 40, Folder 2091)
    - "Blvd de Paris" #2, annotated script, undated (Box 40, Folder 2092)
    - "Blvd de paris" #3, annotated script., undated (Box 40, Folder 2093)
    - "Blvd de Paris" annotated script., undated (Box 40, Folder 2094)
    - "Blvd de Paris" notebook., undated (Box 40, Folder 2095)
    - "Blvd de Paris" notes, undated (Box 40, Folder 2096)
    - "Cafe Amerique" English typed manuscript., undated (Box 40, Folder 2097)
    - "Cafe Amerique" English manuscript., undated (Box 40, Folder 2098)
    - "Cafe Amerique" annotated English script., undated (Box 40, Folder 2099)
    - "Cafe Amerique" annotated working script, English., undated (Box 40, Folder 2100)
    - "Cafe Amerique" original French translation, typed., undated (Box 40, Folder 2101)
    - "Cafe Amerique" Philippe Mikriammos French translation, original typed., undated (Box 40, Folder 2102)
    - "Cafe Amerique" copy of Mikriammos' French translation., undated (Box 40, Folder 2103)
    - "Cafe Amerique" annotated French translation by Brouillon, Burch and Manheim., undated (Box 40, Folder 2104)
    - "Cafe Amerique" annotated French working copy with notes., undated (Box 40, Folder 2105)
    - "Cafe Amerique" notes, undated (Box 40, Folder 2106)
    - "Cafe Amerique" notebook, "II #1" [Box labeled "Cafe Amerique" on end.], undated (Box 43, Folder 2107)
    - "Cafe Amerique" notebook, "II#2", [Box labeled "Cafe Amerique"], undated (Box 43, Folder 2108)
    - "Cafe Amerique" notebook, "II #3" [ Box labeled "Cafe Amerique"], undated (Box 43, Folder 2109)
    - "The Cure" working script., undated (Box 43, Folder 2110)
    - Notebook [filed amidst "The Cure" materials.], undated (Box 43, Folder 2111)
    - "The Cure" annotated script., undated (Box 43, Folder 2112)
    - "The Cure" extra pages., undated (Box 43, Folder 2113)
    - "The Cure" folder and notes, undated (Box 43, Folder 2114)
    - "Classical Therapy" annotated French working script., undated (Box 43, Folder 2115)
    - "Dr. Faustus Lights the Lights" Annotated text, undated (Box 43, Folder 2116)
    - "Dr. Faustus Lights the Lights" English script, undated (Box 43, Folder 2117)
    - "Dr. Faustus Lights the Lights" English script., undated (Box 43, Folder 2118)
    - "Dr. Faustus Lights the Lights" English script and notes., undated (Box 43, Folder 2119)
    - " Dr. Faustus Lights the Lights" annotated French script, undated (Box 43, Folder 2120)
    - "Dr. Faustus Lights the Lights" annotated French script p. 1-7, undated (Box 43, Folder 2121)
    - "Dr. Faustus Lights the Lights" annotated French script p. 10-16, undated (Box 43, Folder 2122)
    - "Dr. Faustus Lights the lights" annotated French script p. 17-28, undated (Box 43, Folder 2123)